<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- This file is part of the book                 -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.  -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- This file is automatically generated from the -->
<!-- private solution manual.  Minor contributed   -->
<!-- edits can be made against this file for       -->
<!-- the purpose of a pull request.                -->
<exercises xml:id="firstlook05-exercises">
    <title>Exercises</title>

		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>Solve the differential equation
					<me>\frac{dy}{dx} + \left(\frac{2}{x} \right) y = \frac{\sin x}{x^2}.</me></p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>

		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>Solve the initial value problem
					<md>
						<mrow>y' &amp; = - \frac{2y}{x + 1} + 2x</mrow>
						<mrow>y(0) &amp; = 2.</mrow>
					</md></p>
			</statement>
			<hint>
				<p><m>y = \dfrac{3 x^{4} + 8 x^{3} + 6 x^{2} + 12}{6 (x + 1)^2}</m></p>
			</hint>
		</exercise>


		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>Solve the initial value problem
					<md>
						<mrow>y' &amp; = - \frac{2y}{1 + x} + e^x</mrow>
						<mrow>y(0) &amp; = 1.</mrow>
					</md></p>
			</statement>
			<hint>
				<p><m>y = (e^x + 1)/(x+1)^2</m></p>
			</hint>
		</exercise>

		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>Solve the initial value problem
					<md>
						<mrow>y' &amp; = - \frac{y}{x + 2} + \frac{\cos x}{x + 2}</mrow>
						<mrow>y(0) &amp; = 1.</mrow>
					</md></p>
			</statement>
			<hint>
				<p><m>y = \sin x / (x + 2)</m></p>
			</hint>
		</exercise>

		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>Solve the initial value problem
					<md>
						<mrow>y' &amp; = y \tan x + \frac{e^x}{\cos x}</mrow>
						<mrow>y(0) &amp; = 1.</mrow>
					</md></p>
			</statement>
			<hint>
				<p><m>y = e^x \sec x</m></p>
			</hint>
		</exercise>

		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>A 600-gallon tank initially contains 200 liters of water containing 10 kilograms of salt.  Supposed that water containing 0.1 kilograms of salt flows into the top of the tank at a rate of 10 liters per minute.  The water in the tank is kept well mixed, and 5 liters per minute are removed from the bottom of the tank.  How much salt is in the tank when the tank is full?</p>
			</statement>
			<hint>
				<p>If <m>x(t)</m> is the amount of salt in the tank at time <m>t</m>, we know that <m>x(0) = 10</m>.  The volume of the tank is <m>V = 600 + 5t</m>.  We can model the amount of salt in the tank at time <m>t</m> with a differential equation,
					<md>
						<mrow>\frac{dx}{dt} &amp; = \text{rate in} - \text{rate out}</mrow>
						<mrow>&amp; = 10(0.1) - 5 \frac{x}{V}</mrow>
						<mrow>&amp; = 1 - 5\frac{x}{600 + 5t}</mrow>
						<mrow>&amp; = 1 - \frac{x}{120 + t}.</mrow>
					</md>
				The resulting equation
					<me>\frac{dx}{dt} + \frac{1}{120 + t}x = 1</me>
				is a first order linear differential equation.  An integrating factor for this equation is given by
					<me>\mu(t) = \exp\left(\int \frac{1}{120 + t} \, dt\right) = 120 + t.</me>
				Multiplying both sides of the differential equation by <m>\mu(t)</m>, we have
					<me>\frac{d}{dt} [(120 + t)x] = (120 + t) \frac{dx}{dt} + x = (120 + t)\left( \frac{dx}{dt} + \frac{1}{120 + t}x \right) = 120 + t.</me>
				Integrating both sides of this equation, we obtain
					<me>(120 + t)x = 120t + \frac{t^2}{2} + C.</me>
				Using the intial condition <m>x(0) = 10</m>, we can determine that <m>C = 1200</m> or
					<me>x(t) = \frac{t^2 + 240t + 2400}{2t + 240}.</me>
				The tank is full at time <m>t = 400/5 = 80</m>, and the tank contains <m>x(80) = 70</m> kilograms of salt when the tank is full.</p>
			</hint>
		</exercise>		

		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>A manager in a communications company contributes <dollar/>2400 per year into her retirement fund by making many small deposits throughout the year.  The fund grows at a rate of 3.5<percent/> per year compounded continuously.  After 35 years, she retires and begins and begins withdrawing from the retirement fund at a rate of <dollar/>3500 per month.  If she does not make any deposits after she retires, how long will her retirement fund last?  [<em>Hint</em>: Divide the problem into two smaller problems<mdash/>one that deals with the situation before retirement and one that deals with the problem after retirement.]</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>		

		<exercise>
			<statement>
	        	<p>Lake Baikal, located in southern Siberia, is only the seventh largest lake in the world in terms of surface area; however, it is the world's deepest lake.  The lake has a depth of 1,642 meters, and the bottom lies 1,186.5 meters below sea level.  Lake Baikal has a volume of 23,600 cubic kilometers and contains 20<percent/> of the world's unfrozen fresh water.  In contrast, Lake Superior, the largest of the Great Lakes, has a volume of only 12,100 cubic kilometers.  Although 544 rivers flow into Lake Baikal, there is only a single outlet, the Angara River.  The outflow of the lake is pretty constant at 60.4 cubic kilometers per year.</p>
	        
	        	<p>Pollution is an increasing concern in Lake Baikal.  One of the major polluters has been Baykalsk Pulp and Paper Mill.  The mill was constructed in 1966 on the shoreline of Lake Baikal and regularly discharged waste into the lake. The plant was closed in November 2008 due to unprofitability, but production resumed in January 2010.  The mill underwent a final bankruptcy in September 2013, but the longterm fate of the mill is still undecided.<fn>Levy, Clifford J. (November 8, 2010). <q>Last Gasp for Factory Bequeathed by Soviets.</q> The New York Times. Retrieved March 14, 2014 from <url href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/09/world/europe/09baikal.html"/>.</fn></p>
	        
	        	<p>Suppose that we wish to understand how the pollution level changes in Lake Baikal over a period of years. Hypothetically, let us assume that the Baykalsk Pulp and Paper Mill has been responsible for most of the pollution in Lake Baikal for the last several decades.  Suppose that at <m>t = 0</m> years the mill ceases operation and there are no longer any pollutants discharged into the lake from the mill although there are still other sources of pollution. Let us assume that the lake is currently 6 times more polluted than these other sources of contaminants.  We wish to know how long it will take for the pollution level to reduce to half of its current level of lake.  Lake Baikal's waters are well-mixed and well-oxygenated in spite of its great depth, so we can model this situation as a simple mixing problem.
	        		<ol>
	       
	        			<li>The volume of water in Lake Baikal is <m>V = 23,600 \text{ km}^3</m>, and
							<me>r_{\text{in}} = r_{\text{out}} = r = 60 \text{ km}^3/\text{year}</me>
						be the rates of inflow from the numerous rivers that feed the lake and outflow to the Angara River.  Assume that <m>C = C_{\text{in}}</m> is the pollutant concentration flowing into Lake Baikal and <m>C_{\text{out}}</m> is the concentration of the outflow into the Angara River (measured in metric tons per cubic km).  If <m>x(t)</m> is the amount of solute at time <m>t</m> in Lake Baikal, then
							<me>x_0 = x(0) = 6CV</me>
						is the initial amount of solute in the lake.  Estimate <m>\Delta x</m> during the time interval <m>[t, t + \Delta t]</m>, where <m>\Delta t &gt; 0</m> is small.</li>

						<li>From your estimate of <m>\Delta x</m> in part (1), write an initial value problem that describes the amount of pollutants in the lake at time <m>t</m>.</li>
				
						<li>The equation that you found in part (2) is a first-order linear equation.  Solve this equation</li>

						<li>Using part (3), predict how many years it will take to reduce the pollution in Lake Baikal to half of its current level.</li>
						
					</ol></p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>	

		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p><em>Variation of Parameters</em>. Consider the following method of solving the general linear equation of the first order,
					<men xml:id="exercise-firstlook05-equation-variation-of-parameters-1">y' + p(t)y = g(t).</men>
					<ol>

						<li>If <m>g(t)</m> is identically zero, show that the solution is
							<me>y = A \exp\left[ - \int p(t) \, dt \right],</me>
						where <m>A</m> is a constant.</li>

						<li>If <m>g(t)</m> is not identically zero, assume that the solution is of the form
							<men xml:id="exercise-firstlook05-equation-variation-of-parameters-2">y = A(t) \exp\left[ - \int p(t) \, dt \right],</men> 
						where <m>A</m> is now a function of <m>t</m>.  By substituting for <m>y</m> in the given differential equation <xref ref="exercise-firstlook05-equation-variation-of-parameters-1"/>, show that <m>A(t)</m> must satisfy the condition
							<men xml:id="exercise-firstlook05-equation-variation-of-parameters-3">A'(t) = g(t) \exp\left[ \int p(t) \, dt \right].</men> </li>

						<li>Find <m>A(t)</m> from Equation <xref ref="exercise-firstlook05-equation-variation-of-parameters-3"/>.  Then substitute for <m>A(t)</m> in equation <xref ref="exercise-firstlook05-equation-variation-of-parameters-2"/> and determine <m>y</m>.  Verify that the solution obtain in this manner agrees with the solution given in the proof of Theorem <xref ref="theorem-firstlook05-first-order-linear-existence"/>.  That is, show that this solution is equivalent to the solution
							<me>y = \frac{1}{\mu(t)} \left( \int \mu(t) g(t) \, dt + C \right),</me>
						where
							<me>\mu(t) = \exp\left(  \int p(t) \, dt \right).</me></li>

					</ol>This technique is know as <em>variation of parameters</em>, which we will revisit when we study second order linear differential equations.</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>		

		<exercise>
			<statement>
			<p><em>Bernoulli's equation</em> is an equation of the form
				<me>y' = a(t) y + f(t) y^n,</me>
			where <m>n \neq 0</m> or 1.  Bernoulli's equation is nonlinear and cannot be solved by the techniques that we have used to solve first order linear equations.<fn>Polking p. 63</fn>
				<ol>

					<li>Using the substitution <m>z = y^{1- n}</m>, show that we can transform Bernoulli's equation into the linear equation
						<me>z' = (1 -n )a(t) z + (1-n) f(t).</me></li>

					<li>Solve the equation <m>xy' + y = x^4y^3</m>.</li>

				</ol></p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>	


		<exercise>  <!--TWJ 3/17/2014-->
			<statement>
				<p>The first-order nonlinear differential equation
					<men xml:id="exercise-firstlook05-equation-ricatti">y' = p(t) + q(t) y + r(t) y^2</men>
				is known as the <em>Ricatti equation</em> and has some useful applications in control theory.  If one solution <m>y_1(t)</m> of the Ricatti equation is known, then a more general solution containing an arbitrary constant can be found by substituting <m>y = y_1(t) + 1/v(t)</m> into equation <xref ref="exercise-firstlook05-equation-ricatti"/> to find a first-order linear equation in <m>v</m> and <m>t</m>, which we can solve to find a general solution to the Ricatti equation.  
					<ol>

						<li>Show that this first-order linear equation is <m>v' + [q(t) + 2 r(t) y_1(t)]v = - r(t)</m>.</li>

						<li>Find the solution to the Ricatti equation
							<me>y' = - \frac{1}{t^2} - \frac{1}{t} y + y^2</me>
						given the particular solution <m>y_1 = 1/t</m>.</li>

						<li>Find the solution to the Ricatti equation
							<me>y' = \cos t - y \tan t + y^2 \sec t</me>
						given the particular solution <m>y_1 = \sin t</m>.</li>

						<li>Find the solution to the Ricatti equation
							<me>y' = 2 - 3y + y^2</me>
						given the particular solution <m>y_1 \equiv 2</m>.</li>

					</ol></p>
			</statement>
			<hint>
				<p><ol>
					
						<li>If <m>y = y_1 + 1/v</m>, then <m>y' = y_1' - v'/v^2</m>.  Substituting into our original equation, we obtain
							<me>y' = y_1' - \frac{v'}{v^2} = p + q y_1 + r y_1^2 - \frac{v'}{v^2}.</me>
						On the other hand,
							<md>
								<mrow>y' &amp; = p + q \left(y_1 + \frac{1}{v}  \right) + r  \left(y_1 + \frac{1}{v}  \right)^2</mrow>
								<mrow> &amp; = p + q y_1 + \frac{q}{v}  + r  y_1^2 + \frac{2r y_1}{v}   + \frac{r}{v^2}</mrow>
								<mrow> &amp; = y_1' +  \frac{q}{v}  + \frac{2r y_1}{v} + \frac{r}{v^2}.</mrow>
							</md>
						Therefore,
							<me>- \frac{v'}{v^2} =  \frac{q}{v}  + \frac{2r y_1}{v}   + \frac{r}{v^2},</me>
						which is just the first-order linear equation
							<me>v' + [q(t) + 2 r(t) y_1(t)]v = - r(t).</me></li>

						<li><me>y = t + \frac{1}{C - t}</me></li>

						<li><me>y(t) = \frac{1}{C \cos t - \sin t} + \sin t</me></li>

						<li><me>y(t) = 2 + \frac{1}{C e^t - 1}</me></li>
					
					</ol></p>
			</hint>
		</exercise>	
		
		<exercise>  <!--TWJ 2/28/2014-->
			<statement>
				<p>Suppose that we have a population that not only grows logistically but also requires a minimum threshold population to survive.  For example, the case of the North Pacific right whale, a species now very much on the endangered list.  If the population drops too low, whales might not be able to find suitable mates and the species will eventually go extinct.  In other words, the population will die out if it drops below a certain threshold.  We can model this with the following equation,
					<men xml:id="exercise-firstlook05-equation-right-whale">\frac{dP}{dt} = k\left(1 - \frac{P}{N} \right) (P - aN),</men>
				where <m>P</m> is the population of the whales at time <m>t</m> and <m>N</m> is the carrying capacity.  The constants <m>k</m> and <m>a</m> are positive with <m>a \lt 1</m>.
					<ol>
					
						<li>Find the equilibrium solutions of the this equation.</li>
						
						<li>Since equation <xref ref="exercise-firstlook05-equation-right-whale"/> is autonomous, we can find a solution using separation of variables.  Find this solution.</li>
						
						<li>Equation <xref ref="exercise-firstlook05-equation-right-whale"/> is also a Ricatti equation  <xref ref="exercise-firstlook05-equation-ricatti"/>.  Since we know an equilibrium solution from part (1), we can use the method of the previous problem to find a general solution to <xref ref="exercise-firstlook05-equation-right-whale"/>.  Find the general solution using the fact that we have a Ricatti equation and show that your solution agrees with the solution that you found in part (2)</li>
						
					</ol></p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>		
	
	</exercises>
