<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- This file is part of the book                 -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.  -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- This file is automatically generated from the -->
<!-- private solution manual.  Minor contributed   -->
<!-- edits can be made against this file for       -->
<!-- the purpose of a pull request.                -->
<exercises xml:id="firstlook07-exercises">
    <title>Exercises</title>
        	
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>Describe the phase line portraits for each of the following equations and how they depend on the parameter <m>\lambda</m>.  Draw the bifurcation diagram for each equation.
				<ol>

					<li><m>y' = \lambda y - \sin y</m> for <m>\lambda &gt; 2 / \pi</m>.</li>

					<li><m>y' = \lambda y^2 - 1</m> for <m>\lambda \in {\mathbb R}</m>.</li>

				</ol></p>
		</statement>

	</exercise>
				
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>Outbreaks of the spruce budworm have been responsible for some major deforestations in Canada and the United States.  The equation
				<me>x' = r \left(  1 - \frac{x}{K} \right) x - c \frac{x^2}{a + x^2}</me>
			has been used to describe the dynamics of spruce budworm populations, where the variable <m>x</m> denotes the population or density of the insect<nbsp/><xref ref="ludwig-1978"/>.  One explanation that has been given for the occurrence of outbreaks is based on the multiple bifurcations that occur with this differential equation.
				<ol>

					<li>If <m>a = 0.01</m>, <m>c = 1</m>, and <m>K = 1</m>, we have a family of differential equations parameterized by <m>r</m>,
						<me>x' = rx(1-x) - \frac{x^2}{0.01 + x^2}.</me>
					Solve the equation equation
						<me>rx(1-x) - \frac{x^2}{0.01 + x^2} = 0</me>
					and plot the result in the <m>xr</m>-plane for <m>0 \leq r \lt 1</m>.</li>

					<li>To find the bifurcation diagram for the spruce budworm equation, reflect the graph obtained in part (1) about the line <m>r= x</m> line.</li>

					<li>Estimate the two bifurcation values from your graph.  Explain what happens to the population as <m>r</m> increases.  That is, when does an outbreak occur?  What happens after an outbreak?</li>

				</ol></p>
		</statement>

	</exercise>
		
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>The differential equation
				<me>\frac{dy}{dt} = y - 4t + y^2 - 8yt + 16 t^2 + 4.</me>
			is not autonomous, separable, or linear; however, we can solve this equation with a change of variable.
				<ol>

					<li>Transform this equation into a new differential equation of the form 
						<me>\frac{du}{dt}= f(u)</me>
 					by letting <m>u = y - 4t</m>.</li>

					<li>Sketch the phase line for this new equation, <m>u' = f(u)</m>, and sketch several solutions.</li>

					<li>Find the solutions of the original differential equation that correspond to the equilibrium solutions of <m>u' = f(u)</m>.  Graph these solutions in <m>ty</m>-plane.  Also, sketch the graphs of the solutions that you plotted in part (b).</li>
					
					<li>Solve the differential new equation and use this information to solve the original differential equation.</li>
			
				</ol></p>
		</statement>

	</exercise>

</exercises>
