<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- This file is part of the book                 -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.  -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- This file is automatically generated from the -->
<!-- private solution manual.  Minor contributed   -->
<!-- edits can be made against this file for       -->
<!-- the purpose of a pull request.                -->
<exercises xml:id="nonlinear01-exercises">
    <title>Exercises</title>

	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>Consider the following three systems<ol>
			
				<li><md>
					<mrow>x' &amp; = 3 \sin x + y</mrow>
					<mrow>y' &amp; = 4x + \cos y - 1</mrow>
				</md></li>
				
				<li><md>
					<mrow>x' &amp; = -3 \sin x + y</mrow>
					<mrow>y' &amp; = 4x + \cos y - 1</mrow>
				</md></li>
				
				<li><md>
					<mrow>x' &amp; = -3 \sin x + y</mrow>
					<mrow>y' &amp; = 4x + 3\cos y - 3</mrow>
				</md></li>
				
			</ol>All three systems have an equilibrium solution at <m>(0, 0)</m>.  Which two systems have phase portraits with the same ``local picture'' near <m>(0, 0)</m>?  Justify your answer.</p>
		</statement>


	</exercise>

	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>Let us consider an epidemic model for a city. We make the following additional assumptions about our model.
	            <ul>

	                <li>The city has a constant birth rate rate of <m>\alpha</m> persons per day. All new born babies are susceptible to the disease.</li>

	                <li>Infected people either recover or die after a certain number of days.  If an individual recovers, he or she is immune.</li>

	            </ul>
	        If we let <m>S(t)</m> be the number of susceptible individuals at time <m>t</m> and <m>I(t)</m> be the number of infected individuals at time <m>t</m>, our assumptions give rise to the following system of differential equations,
	            <md>
	                <mrow>\frac{dS}{dt} &amp; = - \alpha SI + \beta</mrow>
	                <mrow>\frac{dI}{dt} &amp; = - \gamma I + \alpha SI.</mrow>
	            </md>
	        The constant <m>\alpha</m> is determined by the probability of an interaction between a susceptible individual and an infected individual, and <m>\gamma</m> is the rate at which infected individuals are removed from the population. If 
	            <md>
	                <mrow>\frac{dS}{dt} &amp; = - \alpha SI + \beta = 0</mrow>
	                <mrow>\frac{dI}{dt} &amp; = - \gamma I + \alpha SI = 0,</mrow>
	            </md>
			then both the susceptible and infected populations do not change.  This will occur at
	            <md>
	                <mrow>S_0 &amp; = \frac{\gamma}{\alpha}</mrow>
	                <mrow>I_0 &amp; = \frac{\beta}{\gamma}.</mrow>
	            </md>
			We are interested in the behavior of solutions near <m>(S_0, I_0)</m>.  If solutions approach this equilbrium point, then the disease will become endemic to the population.</p>
		</statement>

	</exercise>

</exercises>
