<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- This file is part of the book                 -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.  -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- This file is automatically generated from the -->
<!-- private solution manual.  Minor contributed   -->
<!-- edits can be made against this file for       -->
<!-- the purpose of a pull request.                -->
<exercises xml:id="nonlinear02-exercises">
    <title>Exercises</title>
        	
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>Consider an ideal pendulum with bob mass <m>m</m> and arm length <m>l</m> given by 
				<md>
					<mrow>\frac{d\theta}{dt} &amp; v</mrow>
					<mrow>\frac{dv}{dt} &amp; - \frac{g}{l} \sin \theta.</mrow>
				</md>

				<ol>

					<li>What is the linearization  of the ideal pendulum system at the equilibrium point <m>(0, 0)</m>?</li>
					
					<li>Using <m>g = 9.8</m> m/s<m>^2</m>, how should <m>l</m> and <m>m</m> be chosen so that small swings of the pendulum have period 1 second?</li>

					<li>For the linearization of the ideal pendulum at <m>(0, 0)</m>, the period of oscillation is independent of the amplitude.  Does the same statement hold for the ideal pendulum itself?  Is the period of oscillation the same no matter how high the pendulum swings?  If not, will the period be shorter or longer for high swings?</li>

					<li>An ideal pendulum clock<mdash/> a clock containing an ideal pendulum that ``ticks'' once for each swing of the pendulum arm<mdash/> keeps perfect time when the pendulum makes very high swings.  Will the clock rum fast or slow if the amplitude of the swings is very small?</li>

					<li>If the arm length of the ideal pendulum is doubled from <m>l</m> to <m>2l</m>, what is the effect on the period of small amplitude swinging solutions?</li>

					<li>What is the rate of change of the period of small amplitude swings as <m>l</m> varies?</li>

					<li>Will an ideal pendulum clock that keeps perfect time on earth run fast or slow on the moon?</li>

				</ol></p>
		</statement>

	</exercise>  	
        	
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>Describe the phase portrait for 
			<md>
				<mrow>x' &amp; x^2 - 1</mrow>
				<mrow>y' &amp; -xy + a(x^2 -1),</mrow>
			</md>
			when <m>a \lt 0</m>.</p>
		</statement>

	</exercise>
        	       	
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>Consider the autonomous system
				<md>
					<mrow>x' &amp; y^2 + \cos x</mrow>
					<mrow>y' &amp; 1 + 2x + y \sin x.</mrow>
				</md>
					<ol>

						<li>Show that this system is a Hamiltonian system.</li>

						<li>Find a Hamiltonian function for this system.</li>

					</ol></p>
		</statement>

	</exercise>

</exercises>
