<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- This file is part of the book                 -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.  -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- This file is automatically generated from the -->
<!-- private solution manual.  Minor contributed   -->
<!-- edits can be made against this file for       -->
<!-- the purpose of a pull request.                -->
<exercises xml:id="systems02-exercises">
    <title>Exercises</title>

    <exercise>
        <statement>
            <p>Consider the competing species model
                <md>
                    <mrow>\frac{dx}{dt} &amp; = x(1-x) - \beta xy</mrow>
                    <mrow>\frac{dy}{dt} &amp; = y(1-y) - \beta xy,</mrow>
                </md>
            where the species interact weakly, say <m>\beta = 1/2</m>.
            <ol>

                <li>Find the <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>-nullclines for this system.</li>

                <li>Find all equilibrium points for this system.</li>

                <li>Sketch the phase plane for this system.</li>

                <li>If the inital populations are given by <m>x(0) = 2.4</m> and <m>y(0) = 0.3</m>, what happens to the two populations as <m>t \to \infty</m>?</li>

            </ol></p>
        </statement>


    </exercise>

        <exercise>
        <statement>
            <p>For the following two systems of equations
                <ul>

                    <li>Find the equilibrium points of the system.</li>

                    <li>Sketch the phase plane and direction field for each system using technology.</li>

                    <li>Briefly describe the behavior of typical solutions.</li>

                    </ul>
                    <ol>

                    <li><md>
                    <mrow>x' &amp; = \cos y</mrow>
                    <mrow>y' &amp; = -x + y</mrow>
                    </md></li>

                    <li><md>
                    <mrow>x' &amp; = y</mrow>
                    <mrow>y' &amp; = x - x^3 -y</mrow>
                    </md></li>


                </ol></p>
        </statement>



    </exercise>

    <exercise>
        <statement>
            <p>Consider an epidemic that moves through an isolated population.  We will make the following assumptions about the epidemic.
                <ul>

                    <li>Individuals are infected at a rate proportional to the product of the number of infected and susceptible individuals.  We assume that the constant of proportionality is <m>\alpha</m>.</li>

                    <li>The length of the incubation period is negligible, and infectious individuals are immediately infectious.</li>

                    <li>On the average, an infected individual dies after 10 days.</li>

                    <li>Only a single individual is initially ill.</li>

                    <li>Infected individuals do not give birth, but susceptible individuals have a birth rate of 0.0003 per individual per year.  Newborns are susceptible.</li>

                    </ul>
            If <m>S(t)</m> is the number of susceptible and <m>I(t)</m> is the number of infected people, then
                <mdn>
                    <mrow xml:id="equation-systems02-epidemic-1">\frac{dS}{dt} &amp; = -\alpha SI + 0.0003S</mrow>
                    <mrow xml:id="equation-systems02-epidemic-2">\frac{dI}{dt} &amp; = \alpha SI - 0.1I.</mrow>
                </mdn></p>

            <p>The constant <m>\alpha</m> is a measure of the relative infectivity of the disease.  Some diseases such as Ebola, a viral hemorrhagic fever, are extremely infectious with a mortaility rate of up to 90<percent/>. On the other hand, AIDS which is caused by the HIV virus, has a much lower transmission rate.  The goal of this exercise is to examine the differences between the two.
                <ol>

                    <li>If <m>\alpha = 0.05</m>, draw the phase portrait.  Be sure to label all nullclines and equilibrium solutions.  Suppose that <m>S(0) = 1000</m> and <m>I(0) = 1</m>.  What happens to the solution curve as <m>t \to \infty</m>?</li>

                    <li>If <m>\alpha = 0.000001</m>, draw the phase portrait.  Be sure to label all nullclines and equilibrium solutions.  Suppose that <m>S(0) = 30000</m> and <m>I(0) = 1</m>.  What happens to the solution curve as <m>t \to \infty</m>?</li>

                    <li>What conclusions can you draw about the behavior of the two different epidemics?</li>

                </ol></p>
        </statement>

  

    </exercise>

</exercises>
