<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- This file is part of the book                 -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.  -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- This file is automatically generated from the -->
<!-- private solution manual.  Minor contributed   -->
<!-- edits can be made against this file for       -->
<!-- the purpose of a pull request.                -->
<exercises xml:id="systems01-exercises">
    <title>Exercises</title>

	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>Consider the following predator-prey system,
				<md>
				<mrow>x' &amp; = 2x(1 - x/2) - 1.2xy</mrow>
				<mrow>y' &amp; = -y + 0.9xy,</mrow>
				</md>
			where <m>x(t)</m> is the population of the prey and <m>y(t)</m> is the population of the predator at time <m>t</m>.
				<ol>

					<li>How would you modify this system to include the effect of hunting of the prey at a rate of <m>\alpha</m> units of prey per unit of time?</li>

					<li>How would you modify this system to include the effect of hunting of the predators at a rate proportional to the number of predators?</li>

					<li>Suppose the predators discover a second, unlimited source of food, but they still prefer to eat the primary prey when they can catch them.  How would you modify the system to include this assumption?</li>

					<li>Suppose the predators discover a second source of food that is limited in supply.  How would you modify the system to include this assumption?</li>

					<li>Suppose that the predators migrate to an area if there is more than five times as many prey in that area (<m>x &gt; 5y</m>), and that they move away if there are fewer than five times as many prey as predators.  How would you modify the system to take this into account?</li>

					<li>Suppose that prey move out of an area at a rate proportional to the number of predators in the area.  How would you modify the system to take this into account?</li>

				</ol></p>
		</statement>



	</exercise>

	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>Consider the equation
				<me>\frac{d^2}{dt^2} + \frac{k}{m} y = 0</me>
			for the motion of a simple harmonic oscillator.
				<ol>

					<li>Consider the function <m>y(t) = \cos \beta t</m>.  Under what conditions on <m>\beta</m> is <m>y(t)</m> a solution to the differential equation?</li>

					<li>What initial condition (<m>t = 0</m>) in the <m>yv</m>-plane corresponds to this solution?</li>

					<li>In terms of <m>k</m> and <m>m</m>, what is the period of this solution?</li>

					<li>Sketch the solution curve in the <m>yv</m>-plane that corresponds to this solution.</li>

				</ol></p>
		</statement>



	</exercise>
		
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>A mass weighing 4 pounds stretches a spring 4 inches.
			<ol>

				<li>Consider the function <m>y(t) = \cos \beta t</m>.  Under what conditions on <m>\beta</m> is <m>y(t)</m> a solution to the differential equation?</li>

				<li>Formulate an initial-value problem that corresponds to the motion of this undamped mass-spring system if the mass is extended 1 foot from its rest position and released with no initial velocity.</li>

				<li>Using the result of the previous exercise, find the solution of this initial-value problem.</li>

			</ol></p>
		</statement>



	</exercise>

	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>SEIR model</p>
		</statement>



	</exercise>


</exercises>
