<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                                 -->
<!--                                                               -->
<!-- The Ordinary Differential Equations Project                   -->
<!--                                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2014-2017 Thomas W. Judson 					   -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.                  -->

<frontmatter xml:id="index" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

	<titlepage>
<!--
		<author>
	        <personname>Theron J. Hitchman</personname>
	        <department>Department of Mathematics</department>
	        <institution>University of Northern Iowa</institution>
	        <email>theron.hitchman@uni.edu</email>
    	</author>
-->
		<author>
			<personname>Thomas W. Judson</personname>
			<department>Department of Mathematics and Statistics</department>
			<institution>Stephen F. Austin State University</institution>
			<email>judsontw@sfasu.edu</email>
		</author>

		<date>DRAFT <today /> DRAFT</date>

	</titlepage>

	<colophon>

    <copyright>
        <year>2013-<ndash />2017</year>
        <holder>Thomas W. Judson</holder>
        <minilicense>GFDL License</minilicense>
        <shortlicense>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled <q>GNU Free Documentation License</q>.</shortlicense>
    </copyright>

	</colophon>

	<preface>

		<p>This text is intended for a one-semester undergraduate course in ordinary differential equations.</p>

		<p>There are additional exercises or computer projects at the ends of many of the chapters. The computer projects often require a basic knowledge of programming. All of these exercises and projects are more substantial in nature and allow the exploration of new results and theory.</p>

		<p>Sage (<url href="http://sagemath.org">sagemath.org</url>) is a free, open source, software system for advanced mathematics, which is ideal for assisting with a study of ordinary differential equations. Sage can be used either on your own computer, a local server, or on SageMathCloud (<url href="https://cloud.sagemath.com">https://cloud.sagemath.com</url>). The Sage code has been tested for accuracy with the most recent version available at this time: Sage Version 7.3 (released 2016<ndash />08<ndash />5).</p>

<todo>Check the Sage version.  We are now up to 7.4</todo>

		<!-- check consistency with paragraph above -->
		<sage type="invisible">
			<input>version()</input>
			<output>'SageMath Version 7.3, Release Date: 2016-08-4'</output>
		</sage>


        <attribution>
            <line>Thomas W. Judson</line>
            <line>Stephen F. Austin State University</line>
            <line>Nacogdoches, Texas 2016</line>
        </attribution>

	</preface>

	<acknowledgement>

		<p>This book was written in MathBook XML.</p>

	</acknowledgement>

</frontmatter>