<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                                 -->
<!--                                                               -->
<!-- The Ordinary Differential Equations Project                   -->
<!--                                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2014-2020 Thomas W. Judson                      -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.                  -->

<frontmatter xml:id="index" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <titlepage>
        <author>
            <personname>Thomas W. Judson</personname>
            <department>Department of Mathematics and Statistics</department>
            <institution>Stephen F. Austin State University</institution>
            <email>judsontw@sfasu.edu</email>
        </author>

        <date><today /></date>

    </titlepage>

    <colophon>

    <copyright>
        <year>2013<ndash />2020</year>
        <holder>Thomas W. Judson</holder>
        <minilicense>GFDL License</minilicense>
        <shortlicense>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled <q>GNU Free Documentation License</q>.</shortlicense>
    </copyright>

    </colophon>

    <dedication>
    	<p>To the memory of William Taylor</p>
    </dedication>

    <preface>

        <p>This text is intended for an undergraduate course in ordinary differential equations. <em>The Ordinary Differential Equations Project</em> began when the author was teaching the ordinary differential equations course at Harvard University. After arriving at Stephen F. Austin State University, the Harvard notes began to transform into the makings of a textbook.  At the same time, the author was converting his abstract algebra book, <em>Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications</em> (<url href="http://abstract.pugetsound.edu/index.html">http://abstract.pugetsound.edu/index.html</url>) from LaTeX into MathBook XML (<url href="http://mathbook.pugetsound.edu">http://mathbook.pugetsound.edu</url>). With MathBook XML, which is now PreTeXt, one can produce HTML and PDF versions of a textbook as well as many other formats while only having to maintain the PreTeXt source.</p>

        <p>There has been a strong tend during the past few decades to incorporate technology into undergraduate differential equations courses. Since it is easy to insert computational cells inside an HTML version of the textbook with PreTeXt, there is now an opportunity to seemlessly embed technology into the textbook. Sage (<url href="http://sagemath.org">sagemath.org</url>), our technolgy of choice, is a free, open source, software system for advanced mathematics.  Sage is ideal for assisting with a study of ordinary differential equations, since it cannot only be embedded as computational cells in a textbook, it can also be used on a computer, a local server, or on CoCalc (<url href="https://cocalc.com">https://cocalc.com</url>). The Sage code in <em>The Ordinary Differential Equations Project</em> has been tested for accuracy with the most recent version available at this time: Sage Version 8.7 (released 2019<ndash />03<ndash />23).</p>

        <p>There are additional exercises or projects at the end of many of the sections. Some of the projects may require a basic knowledge of programming. All of these exercises and projects are more substantial in nature and allow the exploration of new results and theory.</p>


        <!-- check consistency with paragraph above -->
        <sage type="invisible">
            <input>version()</input>
            <output>'SageMath Version 8.7, Release Date: 2019-03-23'</output>
        </sage>


        <attribution>
            <line>Thomas W. Judson</line>
            <line>Stephen F. Austin State University</line>
            <line>Nacogdoches, Texas 2019</line>
        </attribution>

    </preface>

    <acknowledgement>

        <p>This book was written in PreTeXt. The open source version of this book has received support from the National Science Foundation (Awards #DUE–1625223 and #DUE-1626455).</p>

    </acknowledgement>

</frontmatter>