<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file is part of the book                                 -->
<!--                                                               -->
<!--    Ordinary Differential Equations Project                    -->
<!--                                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2020 Thomas W. Judson                      -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.                  -->

<references id="references" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  
    <title>Readings and References</title>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="bard-2015">Gregory V. Bard. <title>Sage for Undergraduates</title>. American Mathematical Society, Providence, 2015.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="blanchard-2006">Paul Blanchard, Robert L. Devaney, &amp; Glen R. Hall. <title>Differential Equations</title>, third edition. Brooks/Cole, Pacific Grove, CA, 2006.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="borrelli-2004">Robert L. Borrelli &amp; Courtney S. Coleman. <title>Differential Equations: A Modeling Perspective</title>, Second edition. John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, 2004.</biblio>
        
        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="boyce-2005">William E. Boyce &amp; Richard C. Diprima. <title>Elementary Differential Equations and Boundary Value Problems</title>, Eighth edition. John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, 2005.</biblio>

         <biblio type="raw" xml:id="bauer-2001">Brauer, F. &amp; C. Castillo-Chávez. <title>Mathematical Models in Population Biology and Epidemiology</title>, Texts in Applied Mathematics 40.  Springer, New York, 2001.</biblio>

         <biblio type="raw" xml:id="braun-1992">Martin Braun. <title>Differential Equations and Their Applications: An Introduction to Applied Mathematics</title>, Fourth edition.  Springer-Verlag, New York, 1992.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="britton-2003">Nicholas Britton.  <title>Essential Mathematical Biology</title>.  Springer Undergraduate Series. Springer, New York, 2003.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="burden-2005">Richard L. Burden &amp; Douglas Faires.  <title>Numerical Analysis</title>, Eighth edition Brooks/Cole, Pacific Grove, CA, 2005.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="cheney-2004">Ward Cheney &amp; David Kincaid. <title>Numerical Mathematics and Computing</title>.  Fifth edition. Brooks/Cole, Pacific Grove, CA, 2004.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="edwards-2004">C. Henry Edwards &amp; David E. Penney.  <title>Elementary Differential Equations with Boundary Value Problems</title>.  Fifth edition.  Prentice Hall, Upper Saddle River, NJ, 2004.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="elton-1942">Elton, C. S. &amp; M. Nicholson.  <q>The ten year cycle in the numbers of lynx in Canada,</q>  <title>Journal of Animal Ecology</title>. <volume>11</volume>(1942), pp.215<ndash />244.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="hirsch-2004">Morris W. Hirsch, Stephen Smale, &amp; Robert L. Devaney. <title>Differential Equations, Dynamical Systems, &amp; an Introduction to Chaos</title>, Second edition. Academic Press, San Diego, 2004.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="humphreys-2000">L. D. Humphreys and R. Shammas. Finding unpredictable behavior in a simple ordinary differential equation, <title>College Mathematics Journal</title> 31(2000) 338<ndash />346.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="lazer-1990">A. C. Lazer and P. J. McKenna. Large amplitude periodic oscillations in suspension bridges:  some new connections with nonlinear analysis, <title>SIAM Review</title> 32(1990) 537<ndash />578.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="lorenz-1963">Edward N. Lorenz. <q>Deterministic nonperiodic flow,</q> <title>Journal of Atomospheric Science</title> 20(1963), pp. 130<ndash />141.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="ludwig-1978">Donald Ludwig, Dixon D. Jones, &amp; Crawford S. Holling. <q>Qualitative analysis of insect outbreak systems: the spruce budworm and forest,</q> <title>The Journal of Animal Ecology</title> (1978), pp. 315<ndash />332.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="malcolm-1994">K. W. Malcolm, N. B. Sze, &amp; J. Prather. <q>Better protection of the ozone layer,</q> <title>Nature</title> 367(1994), pp. 505<ndash />508.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="mckenna-1999">P. J. McKenna. Large torsional oscillations in suspension bridges revisited: fixing an old approximation, <title>American Mathematical Monthly</title> 106(1999) 1<ndash />18.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="mckenna-2001">P. J. McKenna and Cillian Ò Tuama. Large torsional oscillations in suspension bridges visited again: vertical forcing creates torsional response, <title>American Mathematical Monthly</title> 108(2001) 738<ndash />745.</biblio>
        
        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="perelson-2002">Perelson, A. S. &amp; P. W. Nelson. <q>Modeling Viral Infections</q> in  <title>An Introduction to Mathematical Modeling in Physiology, Cell Biology, and Immunology</title>.  American Mathematical Society, Providence, 2002.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="polking-2006">John Polking, Albert Boggess, &amp; David Arnold.  <title>Differential Equations with Boundary Value Problems</title>, second edition. Prentice Hall, Upper Saddle River, NJ, 2006.</biblio>

        <biblio type="raw" xml:id="taubes-2008">Clifford Henry Taubes.  <title>Modeling Differential Equations in Biology</title>, second edition. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, U.K., 2008.</biblio>

</references>

