<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                            	   -->
<!--                                                          	   -->
<!--    Ordinary Differential Equations Project      		  	   -->
<!--                                                         	   -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2017 Thomas W. Judson                      -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             	   -->

<section xml:id="secondorder05" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Forced Damped Harmonic Oscillators</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>In Section<nbsp /><xref ref="secondorder04" />, we considered the phenomena of resonance and beats in an undamped harmonic oscillator. Now we will see what happens when we add damping to the system.</p>
    </introduction>

    <subsection>
    	<title>Forced Damped Harmonic Motion</title>

        <p>Suppose that we add forcing to a damped harmonic oscillator,
            <men xml:id="equation-secondorder05-force-damped-1">x'' + 2c x' + \omega_0^2 x = A \cos \omega t. </men>
        The associated homogeneous equation is 
            <men xml:id="equation-secondorder05-force-damped-2">x'' + 2c x' + \omega_0^2 x = 0. </men>
        The characteristic polynomial of <xref ref="equation-secondorder05-force-damped-2" />,
            <men xml:id="equation-secondorder05-force-damped-3">P(\lambda ) = \lambda^2 + 2c \lambda + \omega_0^2,</men>
        has roots
            <me>\lambda = - c \pm \sqrt{c^2 - \omega_0^2}.</me>
        In the underdamped case (<m>c \lt \omega_0</m>), the solution to the homogeneous equation<nbsp /><xref ref="equation-secondorder05-force-damped-2" /> is
            <me>x_h = e^{-ct} (c_1 \cos \eta t + c_2 \sin \eta t),</me>
        where <m>\eta = \sqrt{\omega_0^2 - c^2}</m>.</p>


		<p>To look for a particular solution to <xref ref="equation-secondorder05-force-damped-1" />, we use the complex method.  That is, we shall look for a solution of the form <m>x_c = a e^{i \omega t}</m> to the equation
            <men xml:id="equation-secondorder05-force-damped-4">x_c'' + 2c x_c' + \omega_0^2 x_c = Ae^{i \omega t},</men>
        and then set <m>x_p</m> equal to the real part of our solution.  Substituting <m>x_c</m> into the right-hand side of <xref ref="equation-secondorder05-force-damped-4" />, we obtain
            <me>x_c'' + 2c x_c' + \omega_0^2 x_c = [(i\omega)^2 + 2c(i \omega) + \omega_0^2] a e^{i \omega t} = P(i \omega) a e^{i \omega t},</me>
        where <m>P</m> is the characteristic polynomial<nbsp /><xref ref="equation-secondorder05-force-damped-3" />.  Thus, equation<nbsp /><xref ref="equation-secondorder05-force-damped-4" /> becomes
            <me>P(i \omega) a e^{i \omega t} =  Ae^{i \omega t},</me>
        and
            <me>x_c(t) = a e ^{i \omega t} = \frac{A}{P(i \omega)} e^{i \omega t} =  H(i \omega) A e^{i \omega t},</me>
        where
            <me>H(i \omega) = \frac{1}{P(i \omega)}.</me></p>

	</subsection>

    <subsection>
    	<title>The Transfer Function</title>

		<p>We say that <m>H(\lambda) = 1 / P(\lambda)</m> is the <term>transfer function</term>.  Let us examine <m>H(i \omega)</m> more closely.  First,
            <me>P(i \omega ) = (i\omega)^2 + 2c(i \omega) + \omega_0^2 = (\omega_0^2 - \omega^2) + 2ic \omega.</me>
        If we write <m>P(i \omega)</m> in polar form, then
            <me>P(i \omega) = R e^{i \phi} = R(\cos \phi + i \sin \phi),</me>
        where
            <me>R = \sqrt{(\omega_0^2 - \omega^2)^2 + 4 c^2 \omega^2}</me>
        and <m>\phi</m> is the angle defined by the equations
            <md>
                <mrow>\cos \phi &amp; = \frac{\omega_0^2 - \omega^2}{\sqrt{(\omega_0^2 - \omega^2)^2 - 4 c^2  \omega^2}},</mrow>
                <mrow>\sin \phi &amp; = \frac{2c\omega}{\sqrt{(\omega_0^2 - \omega^2)^2 - 4 c^2  \omega^2}}.</mrow>
            </md>
        Since <m>2 c \omega \gt 0</m>, we know that <m>\sin \phi \gt 0</m>.  Equivalently, <m>0 \lt \phi \lt \pi</m>.  Thus,
            <me>\phi = \phi(\omega) = \cot^{-1} \left( \frac{\omega_0^2 - \omega^2}{2c \omega} \right).</me>
        Therefore, we can write the transfer function as
            <me>H(i \omega) = \frac{1}{P(i \omega)} = \frac{1}{R} e^{-i \phi}.</me>
        We define the <term>gain</term> to be 
            <me>G(\omega) = \frac{1}{R} = \frac{1}{\sqrt{(\omega_0^2 - \omega^2)^2 + 4 c^2 \omega^2}},</me>
        and we will rewrite the transfer function as
            <me>H(i \omega) = G(\omega) e^{-i \phi(\omega)}.</me>
        Thus, the solution to
            <me>x_c'' + 2c x_c' + \omega_0^2 x_c = Ae^{i \omega t}</me>
        is
            <me>x_c(t) = H(i \omega) A e^{i \omega t} = G(\omega) A e^{i(\omega t - \phi)}</me>
        and our particular solution is
            <me>x_p(t) =  \real(x_c(t)) = G(\omega) A \cos(\omega t - \phi ).</me></p>

		<p>It is now clear that <m>x_p</m> is sinusoidal with the same frequency as the forcing term.  In addition, <m>x_p</m> is out of phase with the driving force by the amount
            <me>\phi = \phi(\omega) = \cot^{-1} \left( \frac{\omega_0^2 - \omega^2}{2c \omega}\right).</me></p>
        	
        <p>The general solution to
            <me>x'' + 2c x' + \omega_0^2 x = A \cos \omega t</me>
        is
            <me>x(t) = x_h(t) + x_p(t) = e^{-ct} (c_1 \cos(\eta t) + c_2 \sin(\eta t)) + G(\omega) A \cos(\omega t - \phi ).</me>
        Since <m>x_h</m> has the factor <m>e^{-ct}</m>, the homogeneous part of the solution quickly decays to zero as <m>t \to \infty</m>.  For this reason, <m>x_h</m> is called the <term>transient term</term> while <m>x_p</m> is called the <term>steady-state term</term>.</p>

        <example>
            <p>Consider a harmonic oscillator governed by the equation
                <me>x'' + \frac{7}{5} x' + \frac{3}{5} x = \frac{2}{5} \cos 4t.</me>
            The natural frequency is
                <me>\omega_0 = \sqrt{\frac{3}{5}} \approx 0.7746.</me>
            If we choose the initial conditions so that <m>c_1 = 0</m> and <m>c_2 = 1</m>, our transient term is
                <me>x_h(t) = e^{-ct} \sin \eta t,</me>
            where <m>c = -7/10</m> and
                <me>\eta = \sqrt{\omega_0^2 - c^2} \approx 0.3317.</me>
            Since the gain is <m>G(4) \approx 0.0610</m>, the amplitude of the steady state solution is
                <me>G(4) \cdot \left(  \frac{2}{5} \right) \approx 0.0244.</me>
            The phase is
                <me>\phi = \phi(4) \approx 2.7928.</me>
            The solution and the steady-state solution are given in Figure<nbsp /><xref ref="figure-secondorder05-forced-spring-steady-state" />.</p>

            <p>As we can see, transient solutions can be quite large when compared to steady-state solutions.  Large transient currents can be destructive in electrical circuits.  For example, a light bulb usually burns out when a large transient flows through an already weakened bulb.  This, usually occurs at the time the light bulb is turned out or turned off.  Large transient currents are particularly harmful to the hard drive in a computer.  For this reason, computers should be left on except in the case that they are not being used for a period of several days.</p>

        </example>

        <figure xml:id="figure-secondorder05-forced-spring-steady-state">
            <caption>A forced damped harmonic oscillator and the steady-state solution.</caption>
            <image width="350" source="images/forced-spring-steady-state.png" />
        </figure>

	</subsection>

    <subsection>
    	<title>Amplitude and Phase</title>

		<p>Let us examine the amplitude and phase of the steady-state solution,
            <me>x_p(t) = G(\omega) A \cos(\omega t - \phi),</me>
        where
            <me>G(\omega) = \frac{1}{\sqrt{(\omega_0^2 - \omega^2)^2 + 4 c^2 \omega^2}}.</me>
        Now let <m>s = \omega / \omega_0</m> and <m>D = 2c/\omega_0</m>.  These new constants, <m>s</m> and <m>D</m>, measure the ratio of the driving frequency to the natural frequency and the effect of the damping force, respectively.  Thus,
            <me>G = \frac{1}{\omega_0^2\sqrt{(1- s^2)^2 + D^2 s^2}}</me>
        or
            <me>\omega_0^2G = \frac{1}{\sqrt{(1- s^2)^2 + D^2 s^2}}.</me>
        This expression shows us how the gain varies as <m>s = \omega/\omega_0</m> varies.  The natural frequency is fixed in
            <me>x'' + 2c x' + \omega_0^2 x = A \cos \omega t</me>
        and <m>D = 2c/\omega_0</m> is proportional to the damping constant (Figure<nbsp /><xref ref="figure-secondorder05-forced-spring-gain" />).</p>

		<figure xml:id="figure-secondorder05-forced-spring-gain">
            <caption>The gain of a forced harmonic oscillator with damping.</caption>
            <image width="350" source="images/forced-spring-gain.png" />
        </figure>

	</subsection>

    <subsection>
    	<title>An Application for Washing Machines</title>
       	
        <p>Adjusting the damping parameter for a forced harmonic oscillator can have a dramatic effect on the amplitude of the forced response.  Recent advances in  material science have made it possible to build dashpots that provide a damping coefficient that can be adjusted in real time.  The dashpot is filled with a fluid that changes its characteristics when subjected to a magnetic field.  Such technology can be applied to everyday appliances such as a front loading washing machine (Figure<nbsp /><xref ref="figure-secondorder05-washing-machine" />).</p>

		<figure xml:id="figure-secondorder05-washing-machine">
            <caption>Front loading washing machine.</caption>
            <image width="350" source="images/washing-machine.png" />
        </figure>
            
		<p>The drum of a washing machine spins at many different speeds during its operation.  The spinning provides periodic forcing at various frequencies.  In order to isolate the drum and the effects of periodic forcing from the rest of the washing machine, the drum is suspended inside the washing machine by springs.  During the spin cycle, the drum imparts a periodic forcing to the springs.  This force can have a large amplitude if the load is unbalanced in the drum.  This phenomenon can also occur over a wide range of frequencies.</p>

		<p>The forced response is most dramatic at the resonant frequency of the springs.  In order to keep the machine from shaking too violently at the resonant frequency, dashpots are attached to the springs.  High damping greatly reduces the amplitude of the resonant oscillations; however, stiff dashpots effectively attach the drum to the rest of the machine which can cause the machine to <q>walk</q> across the laundry room floor.</p>

		<p>Let us model how a washing machine might work by considering a harmonic oscillator consisting of a mass of size <m>m = 1</m>,  a spring, a dashpot, and a handle.  Neither the handle or the mass is attached.  The horizontal position of the mass is given by <m>y(t)</m> and the horizontal position of the handle is given by <m>z(t)</m>.  The mass and the handle and the mass are connected by the spring and the dashpot.  The spring constant is <m>k</m>, the rest length of the spring is <m>y_0</m>, and the damping coefficient of the dashpot is <m>b</m>.  We can think of the handle as the rotating drum and the mass as the casing of the washer.  Moving the handle back and forth corresponds to the periodic forcing created by the rotation of the drum.</p>

		<p>We will assume that <m>z(t) = A \cos \omega t</m> is the periodic force applied to the handle.  The other forces acting on the mass are the restoring force from the spring and the damping force from the dashpot.  The spring force is proportional to the difference between the rest length of the spring, <m>y_0</m>, and the actual length, <m>y(t) - z(t)</m>.  The damping force of the dashpot is proportional to the rate at which the mass that the handle are moving together or apart, <m>dy/dt - dz/dt</m>.  Thus, the motion of the mass is governed by the equation,
            <md>
                <mrow>\frac{d^2 y}{dt^2} &amp; = -k(y - z - y_0) - b\left(  \frac{dy}{dt} - \frac{dz}{dt}\right)</mrow>
                <mrow>&amp; = -ky - b \frac{dy}{dt} + kA \cos \omega t - b \omega \sin \omega t + ky_0.</mrow>
            </md>
        We can ignore the term <m>ky_0</m>, since this provides for the displacement of <m>y(t)</m>, and we are only interested in the amplitude of the oscillations.  Thus, our model is
            <me>\frac{d^2y}{dt^2} +b \frac{dy}{dt} + ky = kA \cos \omega t - b \omega \sin \omega t + ky_0.</me></p>

		<p>Using the Method of Undetermined Coefficients, we can find a particular solution to the this equation,
            <me>y_p(t) = A \frac{k^2 - k \omega + b^2 \omega^2}{(k - \omega^2)^2 + b^2 \omega^2} \cos \omega t + A \frac{b \omega^3}{(k - \omega^2)^2 + b^2 \omega^2} \sin \omega t.</me></p>

		<p>Since we are interested in the behavior of our model for different values of <m>b</m> and <m>\omega</m>, we will fix <m>k = 1</m> for convenience.  Hence, our model is now
            <me>y_p(t) = A \frac{1 -  \omega + b^2 \omega^2}{(1 - \omega^2)^2 + b^2 \omega^2} \cos \omega the+ A \frac{b \omega^3}{(1 - \omega^2)^2 + b^2 \omega^2} \sin \omega t.</me>
        We can see what happens as <m>\omega</m> varies for different choices of <m>b</m> from this solution.  If <m>b</m> is small, <m>y(t)</m> has a very large amplitude for <m>\omega</m> near the resonant frequency <m>\omega \approx 1</m>. The response will have a much larger amplitude that the amplitude <m>A</m> of the forcing term.  On the other hand, if <m>b</m> is very large, then the amplitude of <m>y(t)</m> will be close to the amplitude of the forcing term until <m>\omega</m> is very large.<fn>See Figure 4.28 on p. 417 in Paul Blanchard, Robert L. Devaney, and Glen R. Hall. <em>Differential Equations</em>, Second edition. Brooks/Cole, Pacific Grove, CA, 2002.</fn> Now suppose that we install a dashpot with adjustable damping.  We want the damping to be large for <m>\omega</m> near the resonant frequency and small of <m>\omega</m> larger than the resonant frequency.</p>        

	</subsection>

    <subsection>
    	<title>Important Lessons</title>
        	
        <p><ul>
        
        	<li>A forced damped harmonic oscillator,
                <me>x'' + 2c x' + \omega_0^2 x = A \cos \omega t</me>
            has homogeneous solution
                <me>x_h = e^{-ct} (c_1 \cos \eta t + c_2 \sin \eta t),</me>
            where <m>\eta = \sqrt{\omega_0^2 - c^2}</m>.   A particular solution is given by
                <me>x_p(t) = \real(x_c(t)) = G(\omega) A \cos(\omega t - \phi ),</me>
            where the phase angle <m>\phi</m> is
                <me>\phi = \phi(\omega) = \cot^{-1} \left( \frac{\omega_0^2 - \omega^2}{2c \omega} \right)</me>
            and the gain <m>G</m> is given by
                <me>G(\omega) = \frac{1}{\sqrt{(\omega_0^2 - \omega^2)^2 + 4 c^2 \omega^2}}.</me></li>

			<li>The amplitude and phase of the steady-state solution,
                <me>x_p(t) = G(\omega) A \cos(\omega t - \phi),</me>
            are determined by
                <me>\omega_0^2G = \frac{1}{\sqrt{(1- s^2)^2 + D^2 s^2}},</me>
            where <m>\omega = s \omega_0</m> and <m>D = 2c/\omega_0</m>.</li>

		</ul></p>

    </subsection>

    <xi:include href="./exercises/secondorder05.xml" />

    <subsection number="no">
        <title>Project<mdash />The Tacoma Narrows Bridge</title>

        <subsubsection>
            <title>The History of the Tacoma Narrows Bridge</title>

            <p>On July 1, 1940, the Tacoma Narrows Bridge was completed and opened to traffic (Figure<nbsp /><xref ref="figure-secondorder04-tacoma-narrows-bridge" />).  From the first day of operation, the bridge experienced vertical oscillations of several feet.  The bridge received the nickname <q>Galloping Gertie</q> for its wild behavior.  On the morning of November 7, the bridge began undulating up and down with motions as large as three feet.  Later, the bridge began to experience torsional oscillations as large as 23 degrees.  The bridge finally came crashing down at 11:10 a.m.  For a long time, the collapse of the Tacoma Narrows Bridge was attributed to resonance.  However, we shall soon see the the story is more complicated.</p>

            <figure xml:id="figure-secondorder04-tacoma-narrows-bridge">
                <caption>The Tacoma Narrows Bridge</caption>
                <image width="350" source="images/tacoma-narrows-bridge.png" />
            </figure>

            <p>Construction on first Tacoma Narrows Bridge, A.K.A. <q>Galloping Gertie</q>, was completed on July 1, 1940, the bridge was opened to traffic (Figure<nbsp /><xref ref="figure-secondorder06-tacoma-narrows-bridge" />).  Even on the first day of operation, people driving bridge experienced vertical oscillations of several feet.  On the morning of November 7, these vertical oscillations were as large as three feet.  Later that morning, the bridge began to experience torsional oscillations as great as 23 degrees.  The bridge failed castrophically at 11:10 a.m. with the center span falling into Puget Sound below.</p>
            
            <figure xml:id="figure-secondorder06-tacoma-narrows-bridge">
                <image width="350" source="images/Tacoma_Narrows_Bridge_2009.jpg" />
                <caption>The Tacoma Narrows Bridge Video</caption>
            </figure>
            
            <p>There are many interesting stories connected with the first Tacoma Narrows bridge.  One of the insurance policies had been written by a local travel agent who pocketed the premium and failed to report the <dollar />800,000 policy to his company.  During sentencing at his trial, he pointed out that bridge officials had planned to cancel all policies in one more week after which his crime would have never been discovered..  After the collapse of the Tacoma Narrows bridge, the governor of the State of Washington announced, <q>We are going to build the exact same bridge, exactly as before.</q>  Theodore Von Kármán, director of the Guggenheim Aeronautical Laboratory at the California Institute of Technology and a member of the board of inquiry into the collapse,<fn>The Jet Propulsion Laboratory, managed by the California Institute of Technology for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration grew out of the Guggenheim Aeronautical Laboratory.</fn> sent a telegram to the governor stating, <q>If you build the exact same bridge exactly as before, it will fall into the exact same river exactly as before.</q></p>
        </subsubsection>

        <subsubsection>
            <title>The Design of the Narrows Bridge</title>

            <p>The Tacoma Narrows bridge is a suspension bridge like the Golden Gate bridge.  The road bed of the suspension bridge was hung from vertical cables attached to other cables strung between the two towers.  If we think of the cables as long springs, it is tempting to model the oscillations of the road bed with an harmonic oscillator, and one's first guess as to the reason for the collapse of the bridge would be resonance.</p>

            <p>However, the answer may not be so simple.  If the collapse of the bridge was due to resonance, the forcing frequency of a forced harmonic oscillator must be close to its natural frequency, but the wind (the forcing) simply does not behave like this.  One explanation might be the fact that cables are not true springs.  They act more like rubber bands.  Imagine a mass suspended by both a spring and a rubber band.  The rubber band acts like a spring when it is stretched, but there is no restoring force if the oscillator is in a compressed position (Figure<nbsp /><xref ref="figure-secondorder06-spring-rubber-band" />).<fn>For the arguments for and against resonance, consult the references at the end of this section.</fn></p>

    <todo>Fix figure</todo>

            <figure xml:id="figure-secondorder06-spring-rubber-band">

                <caption>A spring-rubber band system</caption>
            </figure>

        </subsubsection>

        <subsubsection>
            <title>The Spring-Rubber Band Model</title>

            <p>Suppose that <m>y(t)</m> is vertical displacement of the mass the spring-rubber band model (Figure<nbsp /><xref ref="figure-secondorder06-spring-rubber-band" />), where the displacement is positive in the downward direction and negative in the upward direction.  We will also assume that we have a damped system.  If this is the case, we can model the motion of the mass with the differential equation 
                <men xml:id="equation-secondorder06-spring-rubber-band-1">my'' = - b y' - k_1 y -  k_2 y^+ + F(t),</men>
            where <m>y^+ = \max(y, 0)</m>.  Here,  <m>m</m> is the mass, <m>b</m> is the damping coefficient, <m>k_1</m> is the spring constant, and <m>F(t)</m> is the forcing term.  The term <m>k_2 y^+</m> corresponds to the rubber band in our system and can be explained as follows:
                <me>y^+(t) =
                \begin{cases}
                y(t), &amp; \text{the rubber band is stretched}, \\
                0,    &amp; \text{the rubber band is slack or tight but not stretched}.
                \end{cases}</me>
            Thus, the rubber band acts as a spring with spring coefficient <m>k_2</m>, if the rubber band is stretched, but has no effect on the system if the rubber band is slack. Of course, the term <m>my''</m> is just an application of Newton's Second law of Motion.</p>

            <p>We can rewrite equation<nbsp /><xref ref="equation-secondorder06-spring-rubber-band-1" /> in the more familiar form
                <men xml:id="equation-secondorder06-spring-rubber-band-2">my'' + b y' + k_1 y +  k_2 y^+ = F(t),</men>      
            Our first observation is that this equation is a nonlinear due to the <m>y^+</m> term.  This may effect how sensitive the system is to initial conditions.  A linear harmonic oscillator is not sensitive to initial conditions.  For example, suppose we consider the harmonic oscillator
                <me>y'' + 2 y' + 2y = \sin t</me>
            and examine the behavior of the solutions for different initial conditions.  In Figure<nbsp /><xref ref="figure-secondorder06-tacoma-solutions-1" />, we give the solutions for <m>y(0) = 0</m> with <m>y'(0) = -4</m>, <m>y'(0) = 1</m>, and <m>y'(0) = 3</m>.  Even though the transient part of the solution can differ a great deal depending on the initial conditions, all of the solutions eventually approach the steady-state solution.</p>

            <figure xml:id="figure-secondorder06-tacoma-solutions-1">
                <caption>Solutions of <m>y'' + 2 y' + 2y = \sin t</m></caption>
                <image width="350" source="images/tacoma-solutions-1.png" />
            </figure>

            <p>Let us return to our spring-rubber band model and let us assume that <m>m = 1</m>. We can rewrite equation<nbsp /><xref ref="equation-secondorder06-spring-rubber-band-2" /> as a system of first-order equations,
                <md>
                    <mrow>y' &amp; = v</mrow>
                    <mrow>v' &amp; = - k_1 y  - k_2 y^+ - b v + F(t)</mrow>
                </md>
            or
                <md>
                    <mrow>x' &amp; = v</mrow>
                    <mrow>v' &amp; = - h(y) -  b v + F(t),</mrow>
                </md>
            where
                <me>h(y)
                =
                \begin{cases}
                k_1 y &amp; \text{if } y \lt 0 \\
                (k_1 + k_2) y &amp; \text{if } y \geq 0.
                \end{cases}</me>
            Let us assume that the forcing term is <m>F(t) = 10 + \lambda \sin \mu t</m>.  If we keep <m>\lambda</m> small and assume that both <m>y(0)</m> and <m>y'(0)</m> are small, there will always be tension on the rubber band.  Or in the case of the Tacoma Narrows Bridge, there will always be tension on the cables of the suspension bridge. However, a large initial velocity such as a gust of wind on the bridge, might cause the cables to go slack.</p>

            <p>To see how this works in practice, we choose constants <m>\lambda = 0.1</m>, <m>\mu = 4</m>, <m>k_1 = 13</m>, <m>k_2 = 4</m>, and <m>b = 0.01</m>, the system becomes
                <md>
                    <mrow>y' &amp; = v</mrow>
                    <mrow>v' &amp; = - h(y) -  0.01v + 10 + 4 \sin 0.1 t</mrow>
                </md>
            where
                <me>h(y)
                =
                \begin{cases}
                13 x &amp; \text{if } x \lt 0 \\
                17 x &amp; \text{if } x \geq 0.
                \end{cases}</me>
            This is a nonautonomous (and nonlinear) system and can be very sensitive to initial conditions.  If we find a numerical solution to this system with <m>y(0) = 0</m> and <m>v(0) = 4.764</m>, we obtain low amplitude solutions (Figure<nbsp /><xref ref="figure-secondorder06-tacoma-solutions-2" />).  However, we only have to change the initial velocity of the system slightly to <m>v(0) = 4.765</m> in order to obtain large amplitude solutions that do not die out over time.</p>

            <figure xml:id="figure-secondorder06-tacoma-solutions-2">
                <caption>Initial conditions <m>y(0) = 0</m> with <m>y'(0) = 4.764</m> and <m>y'(0) = 4.765</m></caption>
                <image width="350" source="images/tacoma-solutions-2a.png" />
                <image width="350" source="images/tacoma-solutions-2b.png" />
            </figure>

        </subsubsection>

        <subsubsection>
            <title>The Bridge Model</title>

            <p>We can now model the bridge by 
                <me>m y'' + \alpha y' + \beta y + \gamma y^+ = -gm + F(t),</me>
            where
                <ul>

                    <li><m>y</m> is the height of the road bed at the center of the bridge.</li>

                    <li><m>m</m> is the mass of the bridge.</li>

                    <li><m>\alpha y'</m> is the damping term.  We assume that <m>\alpha</m> is small since suspension bridges are relatively flexible structures.</li>

                    <li><m>\beta y</m> is the force provided by the material of the bridge pulling the bridge back to <m>y = 0</m>.</li>

                    <li><m>\gamma y^+</m> is the force provided by the pull of the cables.</li>

                    <li><m>-gm</m> is the force provided by gravity.</li>

                    <li><m>F(t)</m> is the periodic force provided by the wind.  Yes, wind does provide a periodic force.  Just think of how a flag flutters in a wind.</li>

                </ul></p>

        </subsubsection>

        <subsubsection>
            <title>The Model for Torsion</title>

            <p>We have still not accounted for the large torsional oscillations that occurred on November 7, 1940, the day that the Tacoma Narrows bridge collapsed.  If we look down the bridge (Figure<nbsp /><xref ref="figure-secondorder06-tacoma-narrows-bridge" />), we see the road bed suspended from two cables<mdash />one on each side of the road.  Thus, we can view a cross-section of the bridge as a rod suspended by cables or springs on each end.  The bar is free to move vertically and rotate about its center of mass.</p>

            <p>If a spring with spring constant <m>k</m> is extended by a distance <m>y</m>, the potential energy is <m>ky^2/2</m>.  Let <m>\theta</m> be the angle of the rod from the horizontal.  If a rod of mass <m>m</m> and length <m>2l</m> rotates about its center of gravity with angular velocity <m>d\theta/dt</m>, then its kinetic energy is given by<fn>Consult your local physicist.</fn>
                <me>\frac{1}{6} m l^2 \left(  \frac{d \theta}{dt} \right)^2.</me>
            The potential due to gravity is <m>-mgy</m>.</p>

            <p>The extension of one spring is given by <m>(y - l \sin \theta)^+</m> and  <m>(y + l \sin \theta)^+</m> in the other, where <m>y^+ = \max(y,0)</m>.  We are making the assumption that the cables remain vertical. Since the cables are relatively long compared to the length of the roadbed, this is a reasonable assumption.</p>

            <p>The total potential energy is given by
                <me>V = \left(\frac{k}{2}\right) \left( \left( (y - l \sin \theta)^+\right)^2 + (y + l \sin \theta)^+ \right)^2 - mgy,</me>
            and the total kinetic energy is given by
                <me>T = \frac{m}{2}   \left(  \frac{dy}{dt}\right)^2 + \frac{1}{6} m l^2 \left(  \frac{d \theta}{dt} \right)^2.</me>
            Let <m>L = T - V</m> and put 
                <me>\frac{d}{dt} \left(  \frac{\delta L}{\delta \theta'} \right) = \frac{\delta L}{\delta \theta}</me>
            and
                <me>\frac{d}{dt} \left(  \frac{\delta L}{\delta y'} \right) = \frac{\delta L}{\delta y}</me>
            where <m>\delta \theta'</m> and <m>\delta y'</m> are small damping terms.  Thus, we obtain the equations
                <md>
                    <mrow>\frac{1}{3} m l^2 \theta'' &amp; = k l \cos \theta [(y - l \sin \theta)^+ - (y + l \sin \theta)^+]</mrow>
                    <mrow>y'' &amp; = -k [(y - l \sin \theta)^+ + (y + l \sin \theta)^+] + mg</mrow>
                </md>
            Since the force exerted by the springs (cables) is not perpendicular to the rod but at an angle <m>\theta</m>, <m>\cos \theta</m> must appear in the first equation.  Adding forcing and damping terms,  we have
                <md>
                    <mrow>\theta'' &amp; = - \delta \theta'  + \frac{3k}{ml}\cos \theta [(y - l \sin \theta)^+ - (y + l \sin \theta)^+]  + F(t)</mrow>
                    <mrow>y'' &amp; = - \delta y' - \frac{k}{m}[(y - l \sin \theta)^+ + (y + l \sin \theta)^+] + g.</mrow>
                </md></p>

            <p>If we assume that the cables never lose tension, then
                <md>
                    <mrow>(y - l \sin \theta)^+ &amp; = y - l \sin \theta</mrow>
                    <mrow>(y + l \sin \theta)^+ &amp; = y + l \sin \theta</mrow>
                </md>
            and we end up with the uncoupled equations
                <md>
                    <mrow>\theta'' &amp; = - \delta \theta'  - \frac{6k}{m}\cos \theta \sin \theta + F(t)</mrow>
                    <mrow>y'' &amp; = - \delta y' - \frac{2k}{m} y + g.</mrow>
                </md>
            The first equation models the torsional motion while the second models the vertical motion.</p>

            <p>If the torsional oscillations are very small, then we can assume that
                <me>\sin \theta \approx \theta \qquad \text{and} \qquad \cos \theta \approx 1,</me>
            or
                <md>
                    <mrow>\theta'' &amp; = - \delta \theta'  - \frac{6k}{m}\theta + F(t)</mrow>
                    <mrow>y'' &amp; = - \delta y' - \frac{2k}{m} y + g,</mrow>
                </md>
            each of which is which is linear.  However, the torsional oscillations for the Narrow bridge were as large as 23 degrees.  The linear model
                <me>\theta'' = - 0.01 \theta'  - (2.4) \theta + (1.2) \sin(0.06 t)</me>
            and the nonlinear model
                <me>\theta'' = - 0.01 \theta'  - (2.4) \cos \theta \sin \theta + (1.2) \sin(0.06 t)</me>
            behave very differently under the initial conditions <m>\theta(0) = 1.2</m> and <m>\theta'(0) = 0</m>.  See Figures<nbsp /><xref ref="figure-secondorder06-tacoma-linear-torsion" /> and <xref ref="figure-secondorder06-tacoma-nonlinear-torsion" /></p>

            <figure xml:id="figure-secondorder06-tacoma-linear-torsion">
                <caption>Solution of the linear model for torsion</caption>
                <image width="350" source="images/tacoma-linear-torsion.png" />
            </figure>

            <figure xml:id="figure-secondorder06-tacoma-nonlinear-torsion">
                <caption>Solution of the nonlinear model for torsion</caption>
                <image width="350" source="images/tacoma-nonlinear-torsion.png" />
            </figure>

        </subsubsection>


    </subsection>

 </section>

<!--</section>-->
